Guide to the Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects records
1952-2010
MS 1939
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
173.1
113 boxes
33,713.39
The records consist of drawings, photographs, correspondence, and administrative and design files associated with the 1977 expansion and renovation of The Museum of Modern Art, as well as other buildings designed by Cesar Pelli and Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects. Also included are project descriptions and fact sheets, press clippings, marketing materials, files documenting buildings designed by Cesar Pelli before he incorporated his own firm in 1977 and other administrative records documenting Cesar Pelli and Associates projects between 1977 and 1979.
Pelli, Cesar
Biographical / Historical
Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects was founded in 1977 by Cesar Pelli, a former associate of Eero Saarinen and Victor Gruen. The firm has received a number of awards and accolades, including the American Institute of Architects' Firm Award and the Aga Khan Award for Architecture. Cesar Pelli was awarded the AIA Gold Medal in 1995. Pelli also served as Dean of the Yale School of Architecture from 1977 to 1984, and was made an honorary Doctor of Arts by Yale University in 2008.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects, 2009-2013. Gift of Will Miller, Irwin Management Company, 2010-2011.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 94-113 are restricted, requiring permission from Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects, until 2033. Electronic records are closed until processed.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in three series: I. Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) Expansion and Renovation, 1952-2007. II. Pre-Cesar Pelli & Associates Project Records, 1965-2010. III. Project Records, Circa 1975-2005. The records were arranged by staff of Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects, and that arrangement has been maintained.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of drawings, photographs, correspondence, and administrative and design files associated with the 1977 expansion and renovation of The Museum of Modern Art in New York. Also included are project descriptions and fact sheets, press clippings, marketing materials, and other project files documenting buildings designed by Cesar Pelli before he incorporated his own firm in 1977. Project records for work undertaken by the firm Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects since 1977 include drawings, correspondence, photographs, project descriptions, marketing materials, and other administrative and design files. Detailed finding aids prepared by staff at Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects also are part of the collection and are filed with individual accessions.
Architecture, American -- 20th Century; Pelli, Cesar; Cesar Pelli and Associates; Daniel, Mann, Johnson & Mendenhall; Gruen Associates; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)
- Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) expansion and renovation (New York, NY) (7701), 1952-2007; Series I
  - General and public relations files
    - Essays and interviews
      - Project explanations [drafts] written by Cesar Pelli (annotations not Pelli's), Circa 1980-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - MoMA Oral History Project: transcript of interview with Cesar Pelli, 1994 March-December (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Assorted interviews and essays, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Audio interview with Cesar Pelli, 1982; 1
        - Use copy (Box 64U)
    - Public relations files
      - Project descriptions, fact sheets, and bibliographies, 1980 January-2001 April (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - MoMA chronologies, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - MoMA program, statements, and reports, 1976-1977 June (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Museum Tower marketing materials, Undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Clippings, 1976-2007 (Box 9, Folder 7-10)
      - Magazines (oversized), 1979, 1984 (Box 12)
      - MoMA 1984 pre-opening coverage book (Box 12)
      - Municipal Art Society exhibit, 1980 June-August (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Assorted materials from PR files, 1977 July-August (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Assorted materials
      - Base/background materials on MoMA, 1975 October-1980 March (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      - General and miscellaneous, 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4-11)
    - Research
      - Lighting research, 1952 May-1975 November (Box 10, Folder 1-8)
      - Museum environmental controls articles, 1976 and undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Printed materials from other museums, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Legal works: McKinney's Consolidated Laws of New York, Book 23, General Municipal Law, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Program materials
    - MoMA program for museum expansion and real estate development, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Memorandum for the Museum of Modern Art to the Trust for Cultural Resources, 1979 July 2 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - MoMA staff and department proposals, 1968 March-1981 June (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Space flow charts, Undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - MoMA area calculations, 1970 January-1977 November (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - CP&A/Gruen area calculations, 1977 February-September (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Schematic plans [three sets], 1977 and undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Sketches of nearby buildings, Undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Administrative files
    - Exploratory and schematic design
      - Cesar Pelli's MoMA files
        - Background materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Chronological files, 1976 October-1977 September (Box 1, Folder 16-25)
        - Miscellaneous materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Fred Clarke's notes
        - Chronological notes, [1977] February-October (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
        - Undated notes (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
        - Assorted materials, 1977 January-April (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - General correspondence
        - Chronological files, 1977 February-October (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
        - Transmittals, 1977 May-October (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Budgets, 1977 March-May (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - General schematics
        - Notes, 1977 May-July (Box 2, Folder 17)
        - Correspondence, 1977 July-August (Box 2, Folder 18)
        - Early schematic plans -- color coded, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Zoning and design feasibility studies
        - CP&A/Gruen zoning studies, 1976 October-1977 August (Box 2, Folder 20)
        - Zoning study from MoMA, 1968 June (Box 2, Folder 21)
        - Legal document, 1967 November (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Community Board Five meeting
        - Draft of memo for community board meeting, 1977 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 23)
        - MoMA statement to Community Board Five, 1977 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Crafts Council building, 1977 July (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Pre-design schedule, Circa 1977 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Assorted noted pertaining to schematic design, 1977 and undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Design development and construction
      - Museum expansion review committee
        - Background documents, 1979 May-1980 April (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Design requests, 1979 September-November (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - Meeting summaries and agendas, 1979 October-1980 November (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
        - File notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Progress reports written by Fred Clarke, 1978 January-1979 March (Box 3, Folder 7-9)
      - Chronological files for special design services, 1977 October-1983 February (Box 3, Folder 10-14)
      - Chronological files for curtain wall, 1981 September-1984 March (Box 69, Folder 9)
      - Chronological files for tower, 1977 June-1981 October (Box 69, Folder 10-16)
      - Correspondence
        - 1977 November-1980 June (Box 3, Folder 15-26)
        - 1980 July-1981 May (Box 4, Folder 1-19)
        - 1981 June-1984 June (Box 5, Folder 1-27)
      - Changes
        - Notes and sketches, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Chronological files, 1981 November-1982 August (Box 6, Folder 2-8)
      - Meeting and design notes
        - 1978 March-1980 March (Box 6, Folder 9-10)
        - 1981 April-1983 December (Box 69, Folder 2-8)
        - Undated (Box 33, Folder 2-3)
      - Design development drawing sets lists of drawings, Undated (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - Design files
    - Site and overall building
      - Site surveys [blueprints], 1962 July-1977 May (Box 15)
      - Shadow studies
        - Sketches, notes, calculations, 1977 April-July (Box 11, Folder 2)
        - Shadow study drawings, Undated (Box 15)
      - Schematic drawings
        - Preliminary space planning diagrams for galleries, 4th, 5th, and 6th floors, and below-grade spaces, 1977 March-April (Box 43)
        - Museum floor plans -- color coded (floors 1-6) [colored pencil on tracing paper], Undated (Box 40)
        - Schematic plans, 1977 July (Box 33, Folder 1)
        - Final schematic design booklet [two copies, one annotated], 1977 October (Box 12)
        - Museum floor plans, sections, and elevations, Undated (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
        - Vertical circulation studies on tracing paper [very fragile], 1977 March (Box 16)
        - Auditorium location studies on tracing paper, Undated (Box 16)
        - Tower location studies on tracing paper, Undated (Box 16)
        - Schematic studies, floor plans, and sections ["rendered MoMA plans"], Undated (Box 16)
        - Schematic studies, floor plans, sections, site study, Undated (Box 17)
      - Design drawings
        - Early design set and assorted design drawings [1.1-1.141, many missing, 2.1-2.3], 1978 February-June (Box 17)
        - Assorted museum floor plans, Undated (Box 18)
        - Engineering floor plans, 1980 June (Box 18)
        - Unidentified axonometric drawings, Undated (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - Final drawings
        - Site plans/site location, Undated (Box 19)
        - Axonometric site plans, Undated (Box 19)
        - Isometric drawing of museum and tower, Undated (Box 19)
        - Final museum floor plans, Undated (Box 19)
        - Longitudinal sections, Undated (Box 19)
        - Section looking north [on tracing paper; drawing is very long], Undated (Box 19)
        - Final site plan, floor plans, and sections [annotated booklet], Undated (Box 12)
    - Exterior elevation/curtain wall
      - Chronological files, 1979 July-1981 September (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
      - Chronological files, No. 11 building, 1981 November-1983 September (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - 53rd Street color elevation studies [colored paper on board], 1977 October-1979 September (Box 6, Folder 14-25)
      - Tower conceptual elevation study: "Syncopated Facade", [1977 Feb] (Box 44)
      - Tower conceptual elevation studies by Fred Clarke and Roger Ferri
        - 1977 April 14, April 20 (Box 10, Folder 17)
        - 1977 April 20-27 (Box 35, Folder 3-5)
        - Undated (Box 37)
      - Tower penthouse conceptual studies [poss. by Cesar Pelli], 1977 May (Box 40)
      - Tower top drawings, Undated (Box 42, Folder 5)
      - 53rd Street elevations by Cesar Pelli, [1977] (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - 53rd Street elevation drawings by Diana Balmori
        - 1977 August-Sep, undated (Box 42, Folder 1-5)
        - 1977 September 16 (Box 43)
        - Undated (Box 45–46)
      - 53rd Street elevation studies [unattributed], 1977 Aug, 1978 Jan, undated (Box 37)
      - 53rd Street elevation drawing with notes [poss. by Fred Clarke], Undated (Box 43)
      - Tower module (facade) studies, Undated (Box 20)
      - Tower and 53rd Street elevation studies on tracing paper, 1978 February and undated (Box 20)
      - Elevations and sections of museum and tower on mylar [south elevation missing]; final curtain wall schemes, 1978-1980 (Box 20–21)
      - Museum exterior design development set [A001-A038], 1978 June-1984 February (Box 33, Folder 7-9)
      - Tower exterior design development set [T001-T017], 1979 September-1980 February (Box 33, Folder 10-11)
      - Assorted conceptual and design drawings, Undated (Box 10, Folder 18-20)
      - Assorted curtain wall design development studies [primarily tower], Undated (Box 33, Folder 5-6)
      - Curtain wall detail drawings, Undated (Box 33, Folder 15)
      - 53rd Street entranceway studies [poss. by Diana Balmori; drawings are very long], Undated (Box 41)
      - West wing north elevation brick pattern studies, Undated (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - Curtain wall cleaning/window washing, 1977 September-1978 June (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Tower interior
      - Condominium floor plan studies, 1977 November (Box 35, Folder 7)
      - Condominium floor plans, 1977 November-1979 August (Box 20)
      - Lobby studies, 1978 January (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Garden hall [includes elevator lobby]
      - Chronological files, 1978 March-1983 July (Box 6, Folder 27-31)
      - Detail drawings [primarily copies of engineers' drawings], 1978 January-1983 November (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
      - Assorted notes, sketches, and research, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Early conceptual sketches by Cesar Pelli, 1977 April (Box 43)
      - Early design development set (3.1-3.27), 1978 March (Box 33, Folder 12-14)
      - Design development set (B001-B052) and assorted design drawings, 1978 June-1983 August (Box 34, Folder 2-7)
      - Structural schematic drawings, 1978 January (Box 23)
      - Section drawings on tracing paper and vellum [drawings are approximately 10 feet long], 1978 January and undated (Box 22)
      - Interior and elevator lobby design development set (C31-C66, many missing) and assorted design drawings, 1977 Dec, 1979 November-1980 Sep, undated (Box 23)
      - Assorted garden hall, elevator lobby, and garden studies on tracing paper; includes planting and paving studies, Undated (Box 23)
      - Exit stair and ramp drawings, Undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Railing and expansion joint drawings, 1981 August-1983 April (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Railing study: handrail and column drawings, 1979 October-1980 April (Box 11, Folder 4-7)
      - Railing study: Blumcraft railing load tests, 1979 October (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Door drawings, 1980 April (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - Escalator notes and drawings, Undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Restaurant/garden wing
      - Correspondence, 1977 July-1981 January (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Notes, 1977 February-1979 June (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Schematic floor plans, Undated (Box 24)
      - Schematic studies of interior and exterior; plans, elevations, sections, Undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Interior and exterior studies; perspectives, elevations, Undated (Box 24)
      - Exterior elevation studies
        - Undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
        - Undated (Box 24)
        - Undated (Box 36)
      - Skylight studies on tracing paper, 1979 October (Box 24)
      - Restaurant floor plan studies
        - Undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
        - 1978 January 18 (Box 26)
      - Design set [D119-D122; D136-D141; D147, plus assorted design drawings], 1981 January-1982 Oct, undated (Box 25)
      - Design set "D", Garden/Restaurant [D001-D020; D022-D037; D039-D041; D042-D069; D071-D077; D082-D121; D123; D125-D135; D142-D146; D148; D060A-D062; D078], 1978 February-1983 December (Box 68, Folder 1-8)
      - Perspectives and elevations of cafeteria/serving area [?], Undated (Box 25)
      - Perspective renderings of restaurant interiors including cafeteria/serving area, public restaurant, and members' restaurant, Undated (Box 26)
      - Assorted sketches and notes, 1978 Feb, 1979 Oct, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Consultants' design proposals and contract agreements, 1977 December-1980 September (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - The George Lang Corporation drawings, 1980 July-November (Box 26)
      - Judith Stockman & Associates drawings, 1980 July-September (Box 26)
    - Marble
      - Chronological file, 1981 April-1982 September (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Slides of marble samples, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Design development set [E138-E154], 1981 August (Box 27)
      - Tile replacement drawing [E150], 1982 January (Box 27)
    - Main lobby
      - Chronological file, 1977 June-1980 May (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - Schematic plans [marker on tracing paper], 1977 June-1977 July (Box 28a)
      - Lobby design development set, F-001 - F-065 [missing F-037], 1978 -1982 (Box 28a)
      - Assorted design development drawings, includes plans and axonometric of information desk, Circa 1980 (Box 28)
      - Lobby furniture/fixture studies
        - [originals], 1979 Dec, undated (Box 27)
        - [blueprints; not duplicates of originals], Undated (Box 28)
      - Bollard studies [ticket receptacle], 1982 September (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Fourth, fifth, and sixth floors
      - Fourth floor [Architecture and Design galleries and study center]: program, 1980 January (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - Fifth floor [Film department and screening rooms]: program requirements, notes, 1979 December-1980 February (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - Fourth, fifth, and sixth floor studies and design development drawings; plans, perspectives, and elevations, 1979 November-1981 May (Box 29)
      - Library studies; perspectives, plans, and elevations on tracing paper, Undated (Box 29)
      - Design drawings of library, study centers, and administration areas; perspectives, plans, and elevations, 1980 June-1981 April (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Auditorium
      - Floor plans, 1984 February-March (Box 30)
      - Design development set [G001-G034]; plans, sections, and elevations, 1978 July-1983 August (Box 34, Folder 9-10)
      - Studies; plans, sections, and perspectives, 1979 October-Dec, undated (Box 30)
      - Auditorium lobby studies; perspectives, plans, elevations, elevator elevations, 1980 Nov, 1983 Sept, undated (Box 30)
      - Auditorium interior fixtures design development (exit signs, ticket receptacles), 1981 October-1984 April (Box 34, Folder 11)
      - Assorted drawings, 1977 June-1979 Dec, undated (Box 34, Folder 11)
      - Assorted sketches and notes, 1984 Feb, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Museum store [bookstore]
      - Design development set "1", 1979 December-1983 February (Box 31)
      - Assorted design drawings; plans, perspectives, axonometric, elevations [originals], 1980 Jan, 1981 Mar, undated (Box 38)
      - Assorted design drawings; plans, elevations [blueprints, sepias], 1980 July-1984 Feb, undated (Box 32)
      - Studies [tracing paper], 1979 October-1980 October, undated (Box 32)
    - Galleries: drawings [vellum], 1980 May, undated (Box 34, Folder 12-13)
    - Group reception space: studies and design drawings, 1979 November-1980 Dec, undated (Box 39)
    - Ceramic tile
      - Tile work specifications, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1980 August-1982 September (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Notes, research, and manufacturer information, 1981 August-1982 March (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Interior design, 1979 December-1981 March
      - Notes, correspondence, manufacturer information, 1979 December-1981 March (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Detail drawings of doors and partitions, 1980 March (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Public restrooms: design development set [H001-H019], 1979 September-1981 March (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Temporary/miscellaneous
      - Design development set (M001-M025), 1979 July-1980 March (Box 34, Folder 15-16)
      - Drawing of exhibition model [?], [1979] (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Consultants
    - Structural engineering [7701.51]: chronological files, 1977 November-1983 November (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Exiting [7701.52]
      - Stair studies, 1977 November (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Chronological files, 1977 November-1982 December (Box 7, Folder 15-18)
    - Mechanical engineering [7701.53]
      - Steam source preliminary feasibility study, 1977 December (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Outline descriptions of mechanical systems, 1978 February (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - Chronological files, 1977 December-1984 April (Box 7, Folder 21-22)
      - Cooling tower locations drawings, 1979 February (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Lighting [7701.54]
      - Philip Johnson correspondence, 1963 October (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Chronological files, 1977 December-1983 November (Box 8, Folder 2-18)
      - Photos of Don Bliss lighting boards, Undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Landscape geotechnical [7701.55], 1977 May-1984 March (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Wind tunnel [7701.56], 1978 January-1979 September (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Acoustical [7701.57]
      - Reports, 1979 Nov, 1982 August (Box 8, Folder 21)
      - Chronological files, 1977 December-1982 August (Box 8, Folder 22-23)
      - Assorted items and product information, Undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Graphics [7701.58]
      - Chronological files [bulk are drawings], 1981 June-October (Box 8, Folder 25)
      - MoMA signage program [booklet], Undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Photographic and moving images
    - Cesar Pelli/office images, [1977-1984] (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Pre-design/research images of historic MoMA and existing conditions, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Design images
      - Site/overall building
        - Shadow studies: images of drawings, [1977] (Box 13, Folder 3)
        - Site plan [prints and slides], Undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
        - Final sections: north, east, and west [prints], Undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
        - Final museum floor plans, Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
        - Site plans, sections, floor plans [not final], Undated (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
        - Renderings of exterior and garden hall, Undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
        - Models: prints, transparencies, slides, Undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
        - Models: contact sheets, 1978 June-August (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Exterior elevation/curtain wall
        - Tower massing study models, [1977] (Box 13, Folder 12)
        - Facade study drawings, [1977] (Box 13, Folder 13)
        - Model with color elevation studies, [1977] (Box 13, Folder 14)
        - Curtain wall mock-ups, 1981 November (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - Garden hall
        - Study and final models [slides], [1977] (Box 13, Folder 15)
        - Structural detail drawings [prints], Undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Restaurant/garden wing: study models of exterior, Undated (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Main lobby: models of furniture arrangements, Undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
      - Marble samples [slides], Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Gallery/art work layout [slide], Undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Consultant images: Don Bliss lighting boards, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Construction images
      - Slides and prints, 1981 Jun, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Book of construction progress photographs, 1980 January-1981 April (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Final photography
      - Kenneth Champlin: negatives and contact sheets, Circa 1984 (Box 14, Folder 3)